Guide to the Charles Robert Leslie Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Correspondence, Series III
  - Charles Robert Leslie
    - Letter to Thomas Leslie, 1812 February 2; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 6 pages (2 folded leaves); 32 x 40 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Leslie mentions some new acquaintances in Turnham Green, including a family called the Collets and a Dr Rogers. He notes that a Mr Jennings in London, a "picture cleaner," remembers his father and has emigrated from Philadelphia himself. He also mentions a family called the Earles and a Miss Daghton, "daughter of the actor of that name," and sister to a painter who has won a prize at the academy. Leslie writes of a Mr Alston, "a young American artist of very fine talents," with whom he and Morse spend time.
      Leslie writes of a "new play by Reynolds...called the 'Origin of the Sun.'" He mentions some current reviews of the play and assures Thomas that he will soon be able to see it "on the other side of the water."
      Leslie notes British opinion of the way "Congress are proceeding," and mentions that he is glad of the "spirit" of his "countrymen." He plans to stay in London even if "any thing serious should take place," but fears being cut off from contact with his family and friends. He hopes that the current tension is "only talk" and will be resolved when "the Prince Regent comes to the full exercise of his powers" later in the month.
      Leslie notes that he has already sent a letter "to Mama," with "sketches of Mrs Siddons & Kemble," and then includes a sketch for Thomas in this letter. The title is obscured, however. He mentions having also written to Betsy with "the notes of 'Soldier Rest'."
      Leslie comments that "[t]here were six people hung here a few days ago and not one of them for murder," and remarks on the high crime rate in London. He asks Thomas to relay some messages and his affection to mutual friends and family members. He asks for Thomas to write him long letters and to include "every little thing that you can relate," as he is hungry for news of home and knows that Thomas does not have as many correspondents expecting letters as he himself, being abroad, does.
      Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Panoramas; Leslie, Thomas Jefferson, 1796 or 1797-1874 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820
    - Letter to Harriet Stone Leslie, 1834 May 27; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 37 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The letter is postmarked from Petworth on 27/28 May, 1834 and is addressed to "Mrs. Leslie" at 41 Portman Place, Edgware Road, London. Leslie writes to his wife about his ride to the area, saying that it was quite dusty. He may have been traveling in order to fulfill a commission, possibly to paint portraits. He describes meeting a Mrs. Rydsdale and her children at the house where he is staying, commenting that she will be "delighted at the prospect of seeing you soon again." Leslie also writes of being received by Lord Egremont, seeing a Mrs. King and her children, a Colonel Henry, Lady George Townshead [?], Lady Emily and the Miss Rydsdales. He also mentions a Mr. Morrison as being "the gentleman for whom I did not paint a picture..." He writes of missing his wife and of trying to get home as soon as possible. It seems that Harriet might have been ill or have been burdened with caring for her growing family at this time, for Leslie advises her with great emphasis to take care of herself and to rest as much as possible while he is away. He describes some sort of enormous fete in town, at which "4 or 5 thousand" women and children came to dine and were waited upon by men. He closes by commenting somewhat cryptically on a person in the household (perhaps a servant?) called "Cupid" who asks about the family but who may have a "rival in New York."
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Harriet Leslie, 1844 May 14-15; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 37 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Leslie and his wife write to their daughter from Brussels, where they are staying. Leslie writes first, commenting on the impressive Catholic churches and services there, and in particular on the music. He goes into great detail about the various services and forms of music performed in church. He includes a description and small ink sketch of a figure representing the Virgin Mary, over whose head "is a large halo of silver stars." He also writes of visiting the Royal Castle of Laeken, saying of "the palace of Leopold" that "as he is at present there, we could only see the outside which is very handsome." Leslie expresses disappointment that "we have not seen many first rate pictures," but he hopes to see some later on when he and his wife travel to Cologne, Frankfort, Holland, and back to Belgium to see Antwerp. Harriet Stone Leslie then takes over the pen and inquires about her daughter's health and the situation at home. She comments briefly on what souvenirs she is contemplating purchasing for the children. A final note, seemingly in C.R. Leslie's hand, appears at the very end of the letter, penned on May 15th. The letter is postmarked May 15, 1844 and sent to Harriet Leslie at 12 Pine Apple Place, Edgware Road, London.
      Brussels (Belgium); Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to H. Burton, 1847 May 22; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859; 1 page (1 leaf); 18 x 12 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Leslie writes to thank Burton for payment received (60 guineas) for Leslie's "little picture of the [illegible] girl." The work in question is probably Leslie's Girl in a Coblentz cap, with lillies of the valley in her hand. According to the appendix of Leslie's Autobiographical recollections, this work was painted in 1845 for Robert Burton, Esq., New York.
      The present letter was removed from the library's copy of Autobiographical recollections.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence
  - Harriet Jane Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert and Harriet Stone Leslie, 1835 October 9; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 37 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Harriet writes to her parents from school, thanking them for their letter and wishing she could be home. She expresses desire to see "the telescope" and "dear little baby," who may be George Dunlop Leslie. She reports having been on several walks for "blackberrying" and says that there are several new girls at school this quarter. She again writes of missing her family and wanting to "nurse the baby." She includes Caroline's love in closing the letter.
      On the last two pages of the letter is a cross-written note from an adult, signed "S. __tforth (possibly Cutforth?)." The letter has been addressed in this adult's hand to "Mr. Leslie," care of the "Earl of Egremont, Petworth, Sussex." The writer seems to be a Quaker and addresses Leslie as "Dear Friend," referring to him as "thee" throughout. The writer discusses the children's good behavior and comments on clothing purchased recently for them and that they will require in the future. Some sort of travel arrangement to London is also discussed. It is not clear what the relationship of this person is to Harriet or her school in Berkhamsted. The date on the letter, also in this writer's hand, is written out as "9th of 10th mo, 1835," suggesting the Quaker tendency not to use month names.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert and Harriet Stone Leslie, 1836 January 23; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Harriet writes her parents from school in Berkhamsted. She thanks them for their recent letter and hopes that her Aunt Sarah is recovering. She reports on a friend's birthday, in honor of which the "governess gave the girls a treat." She declares that she is happy at school but looks forward to reuniting with her family at midsummer. Harriet remarks that her chilblains are better but that "we have had little colds," and goes on to include Caroline in sending love to her parents, suggesting that she and Caroline were at school together. Harriet mentions, cryptically, that "I am requested by Governess to say that I have not had any port wine."
      Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Robert Charles and Charles Robert Leslie, with additional note from Bradford Leslie to R.C. Leslie, circa 1835-45; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.2 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      On the first page of this letter, Harriet writes to tell her brother Robert about a ship, a "large East India man [sic] came into Portsmouth yesterday." Knowing of Robert's interest in ships, she provides details on the vessel, which is called, "The Prince of Walse [sic]" and is "frigate built." She goes on to write to her father on the following pages of the letter. Mary, who seems to be staying with her mother and siblings, relays a message telling her father that "Mr. Waters...is to clean the chicken house..." along with select other chores. She reports that their piano has arrived and that they will not have to overhear the demolition of a local church, which will happen in six weeks' time. She says that a Mr. Wallis will pilot the "Prince of Wales" ship that she has mentioned to Robert. Harriet reports on Mary and George's sketching and asks her father to "send Macbeth for me" along with another book. She comments on the Wallises' plums before closing. Bradford Leslie pens a small note on the last page, asking his brother Robert to send "my schooner...and also a piece of wood to make her spars..."
      Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Robert Charles, 1826- -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, circa 1840-1855; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 22.5 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Harriet reports calling upon a Miss Rogers and talking with her about an election. A Mr. Jones was not elected and Miss Rogers claims that "it was the Queen's doing." There is some concern about "the Jones[es] escap[ing] skin free & spotless..." Harriet goes on to discuss further social calls and correspondence. She inquires about her brother Bradford's face (it seems to have been injured) and comments on other mutual acquaintances. Harriet worries about someone called Ann, who seems unable to save her money, and expresses her worry about Leslie's having "[given] a picture for her," the value of which, she feels, would have been better allocated to his own children, who have to "look at every farthing." She continues badgering her father about Ann's wasteful spending habits. She closes affectionately, but the letter seems to reveal considerable anxiety about the family's finances.
      Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Jane, 1828-1864 -- Correspondence
  - Harriet Stone Leslie
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1836 August 10; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 23.4 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and blue ink. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Harriet writes from Bromyard, Herefordshire, saying that she misses her family and fears being forgotten by "the little ones," but that a trip to the seaside (whence she writes) will "patch me quite up for the whole winter..." She inquires after the children at home (it seems that Robert is with her) and sends instructions for their care. She writes repetitively of coming home and sets a date for her return. Harriet comments on being in Malvern, saying that she went to the library and scanned the visitors' list but did not see a Miss Wilkie or Lady Laurie. Harriet closes but then adds an odd postscript about her dislike for widows who remarry and closes again with some instructions for their daughter, Harriet.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1838 December 14; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 1 page (1 folded leaf); 22.5 x 37 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Harriet writes a brief letter to her husband, reporting that Mr. and Mrs. Brown have just left, and that a Mr. Humphrey "has been all sufficient to Miss Bacon..." She reports further that "Mr. Brown says his Excellency the American Minister Mr. Stephenson & his Lady are to pay a visit to the Castle..." Letter is addressed to Leslie first at the Castle Hotel in Windsor, but this is crossed out, along with an address to Leslie at the Royal Academy. Ultimately, the letter was sent to Leslie at home, at 12 Pine Apple Place in Edgware, London.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, circa 1840; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.2 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and black ink (considerably faded). (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Harriet writes while away from home, likely on a seaside holiday with the children. She begins with a little note recommending that Leslie not fold his letters "so wide apart." She says that she is glad to have been away while Irving was visiting Leslie, for she suspects that the former is "jealous" of her and would prefer Leslie to have remained a bachelor. She amends her remark by stating that she is sure Irving likes her as much as she likes him. Harriet comments on the children's sketching and swimming. She remarks that she is sorry that Leslie's picture "has been so much interrupted," but that she is glad that Irving was pleased with "the St. John's head" in this painting. Harriet closes with a postscript saying, "I dont think you read all my stuff--I forgive you--but burn these."
      Correspondence; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879 -- Correspondence; Leslie, Charles Robert, 1794-1859 -- Correspondence
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, circa 1840; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 17.5 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Harriet writes from Sandgate, in Kent, dating her letter "October 23." She bemoans the wintery weather, but counters the gloomy account with a report of a "charming drive to Saltwood Castle in Mrs Foster's carriage..." She remarks that she is glad that Charles has found his spectacles and asks where they were. She tells her husband to relay a message to their daughter, Harriet, about the curtains for the house, saying that they must be suited to the Leslies' means and standing, or else will be vulgar. She gives further direction about cooking and remarks that "[a] beggar has just appeared in sailors clothes..." outside, shortly before closing the letter. She advises Charles to keep warm on the sofa.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, circa 1840; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Harriet writes home to report various woes, among them poor weather and bad food. She remarks that a family called the Fosters are "just passed," having left Harriet and the children "strangers in a strange land." Mention of the Fosters in another letter addressed from Sandgate, Kent, suggests that this letter also comes from the same place and dates from the same time. Harriet acknowledges that she complains a lot, but notes that the place where she is staying is more expensive and of poorer quality than London. She reports on buying Bradford some rubber boots and asks for a piece of sewing work to be sent to her. She complains again about the rain and then requests her husband to call on a "Mr Gray" to tell him of her disappointment with a dress that he has made for her. She relays some orders for the servant, Susan, and asks Leslie not to send more potted meats. Letter is dated "Thursday" only.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1841 or 1851, possibly April; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 1 extant page, (1 leaf); 22.5 x 18.5 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Letter addressed to "CR Leslie Esq RA" at 71 Parrock Street, Gravesend. Postmark is partially obscured and the letter does not appear complete. Harriet writes of someone going to America, saying that the person will undoubtedly gain experience he lacks by being robbed, for "a Thief, is about the first gentleman he shall meet [in] America." She says that she has written to Rose Baron, stating that when she writes the name she is reminded of Lord Byron's verse. Harriet asks Leslie to relay a message to Bradford and comments on domestic matters. She closes by commenting on her worry over George and someone called Polly, who are sailing. She adds a postscript directing Leslie to "Burn all this rubbish."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1844 September 2; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 23 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Letter is postmarked from Ryde, in the Isle of Wight. Harriet is concerned that Leslie is being made ill by his paint, and advises that Robert can take Bradford's bed from their room. She frets about Leslie's health, worrying about him being left alone. She asks for Robert to bring her "Machine as I have not quite recovered my sea sickness. I am so giddy & assure you I have not drunk any beer, it is not good enough." She passes on a criticism of Susan, a servant, for forgetting an item in a parcel for Harriet. She bemoans George and Bradford's new friendship with an "idle" boy in town, asking Leslie to write them of his great expectations for them and to require them to write "an abridgment of each separate life as they read it..." She comments on some porcelain brush handles that Leslie seems to be ready to purchase, hopes that Susan will manage the apples on the tree at home, and also hopes that Leslie will enjoy an upcoming trip after remembering to "wrap up the old Plates" in advance of some home improvement to be done.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1844 September; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 23.5 x 38 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Letter is postmarked from Ryde, in the Isle of Wight. Harriet writes in a playful tone, teasing Leslie about getting "puffed up" on praise. She thanks him for sending some vermillion and is glad that he has killed a rat at their home. Harriet advises Leslie on some domestic issues with the servants, telling him how to handle Susan, who has her faults. She inquires about his progress with a painting, encouraging him to finish it. She asks him to write to their son Bradford and challenge him to a drawing or painting contest with his brother Robert. Harriet remarks on her health and closes with a request for a dresser or cabinet to be built with a closing door. She includes a tiny sketch of the furniture piece.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1846 September 14; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 23 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Harriet writes to C.R. Leslie while away from home, probably on a seaside holiday with the children. She comments that she has written him recently and mentioned a house to let that has been taken in the meantime. She says that there "is not a lodging, or house to let in this place..." She mentions that "Mary and H. bathe every day..." and comments that someone called "Sam" left town for London, suffering with a stomach ache that only improved with a "table spoonful" of "Daffy's Elixir," a popular cure-all of the era. Harriet remarks that she has expressed her feelings on "the engraver, I hope you will hold up your head, till I return, & then I will hold it up for you..." It seems that there is some kind of financial dispute afoot. Harriet also writes of the children's artistic education, hoping that Robert can attend drawing school in the evening and that Mary will get some much-needed "tuition." Harriet comments on having to alter dresses made recently by a local dressmaker, advising Leslie sharply not to mention the problem to the dressmaker but to have their daughter Caroline pay close attention to the fitting of her own dress. Harriet closes with a postscript asking for Caroline to send some cayenne pepper and hoping that she will eat oatmeal porridge for tea.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, 1848 August 18; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf, with last page partially torn off); 18 x 22.6 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Harriet writes from St. Albans Bank, saying that it is lovely and that she wishes she could have Charles, George, Bradford, Robert, and Caroline with her. She mentions Robert's return trip and hopes that he has "got over his annoyance about the Cab..." She asks for Caroline to have the servants wash and press "my lilac flounced dress" and for Charles to bring it with him when he comes, "with the clogs india Rubber ones [sic]," and to send a note from Mary along to Annie Beale. She comments on her restful sleep and expresses her wish that Charles will join them if they stay in St. Albans Bank longer. She closes by saying the letter is written in great haste and adds a note on the outside page to request a sketch book be sent.
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, early 1840s, "Friday Oct 2nd"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 3 pages (1 folded leaf); 18.5 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and brown/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Harriet labels the date on the letter, "wet day," and begins by bemoaning the wet weather. She advises Charles that she and the children will be home "on Monday," and sends various instructions for the servant, Amelia. She requests 20 pounds to pay the bills from the holiday and apologizes for the amount, however commenting that "it is all fair play." She sends love from Aunt Clark, whose eyes are better. Harriet closes with a list of expenses, one of which is "Breakage."
    - Letter to Charles Robert Leslie, probably 1840s, "Sunday Eve"; Leslie, Harriet Honor Stone, 1799-1879; 4 pages (1 folded leaf); 18 x 22 cm. Autograph letter, signed; written in pen and blue/black ink. (Box 1, Folder 21)